<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Cartography | mattmakesmaps]]></title>
  <link href="http://mkgeomatics.github.io/blog/categories/cartography/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mkgeomatics.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-05T17:35:29-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://mkgeomatics.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Matthew Kenny]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[matthewkenny AT gmail DOT com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hand-Rolled Vector Tiles - TileStache]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkgeomatics.github.io/blog/2011/02/25/hand-rolled-vector-tiles-tilestache/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-25T05:09:52-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkgeomatics.github.io/blog/2011/02/25/hand-rolled-vector-tiles-tilestache</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago I found myself surfing the intertubes for instructions on how to serve up some vector tile goodness. That search came up pretty much empty, except for one glimmering <a href="http://gis.stackexchange.com/questions/3712/create-vector-geojson-tiles-for-polymaps">thread</a> of hope. The answer, <a href="http://tilestache.org/">TileStache</a> { &lt;-- Imagine that's a mustache on it's side.</p>

<blockquote><p>TileStache is a Python-based server application that can serve up map tiles based on rendered geographic data.</p></blockquote>

<!-- more -->


<p>By design, TileStache can be used to serve up stylish TMS tiles using <a href="http://mapnik.org/">mapnik</a> map files, and can also be used to locally cache remote-services via <a href="http://tilestache.org/doc/#providers">proxy</a>. What I'm most interested in though, is it's ability to deploy vector tiles. So what are vector tiles? Think TMS tiles... but replace representations of the geometries through images, with <a href="http://geojson.org/">GeoJSON</a>. Pretty wild right? Specifically, the TileStache <a href="http://tilestache.org/doc/TileStache.Goodies.Providers.PostGeoJSON.html">PostGeoJSON Provider</a> can be used to connect TileStache to a PostGIS data source, and return a tile comprised entirely of GeoJSON data.</p>

<p>For example, data from a PostGIS data source can be rendered as an image tile (.../10/16/357.png), like this:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.mkgeomatics.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/tile.png"><img src="http://www.mkgeomatics.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/tile.png" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>But can also be represtented as a vector tile (.../10/16/357.json), like this:</p>

<p>``` javascript
// Subset of a single 256x256 pixel vector tile.
{
  "type": "FeatureCollection",
  "features": [</p>

<pre><code>{
  "geometry": {
    "type": "MultiPolygon",
    "coordinates": [
      [
        [
          [
            -122.973093,
            47.969842
          ],...
          [
            -122.973093,
            47.969842
          ]
        ]
      ]
    ]
  },
  "type": "Feature",
  "properties": {
    "property_s": "USFS",
    "juris_name": "Olympic National Forest"
  },
  "id": 1280
}
</code></pre>

<p>  ]
}
```</p>

<p>So what are the advantages of using vector tiles? You can already use <a href="http://dev.openlayers.org/docs/files/OpenLayers/Format/GeoJSON-js.html">OpenLayers' GeoJSON</a> format reader to populate a vector layer in OL. It's an issue of size. Highly complex geometries can be large in size, and requesting all that data at once can be time consuming. Vector tiles approach this problem using the same answer as TMS... only request those sections of data which you need at that time. By only requesting those tiles within the user's current extent + a small buffer, the need to download large geometries at once can be negated. Furthermore, just as TMS's can be pre-cached to disk (seeded), so can vector tiles.</p>

<p>One example of this is serving up a combined NFS boundary dataset compiled by my good pal, Greg (<a href="http://www.chopshopgeo.com/blog/">http://www.chopshopgeo.com/blog/</a>). These boundaries are <strong>dense</strong> and displaying them at their full extent &amp; raw level of detail is expensive. But by breaking the vector representations of these geometries up into a standard tile scheme, only those tiles which we need are requested, and only when we need them. As a side note, in addition to tiling, I also simplified the boundaries, to promote faster load time at small-scales. The least granular vector representations display at the smallest zoom-scales, while the highest (raw, unsimplified) level of granularity displays only at the largest zoom-scales.</p>

<p>[caption id="attachment_398" align="alignnone" width="665" caption="NFS Boundaries Provided By ChopShopGeo"]<a href="http://www.mkgeomatics.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/parks.png"><img src="http://www.mkgeomatics.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/parks.png" alt="" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>Additionally, using vector representations of geometry rather then cached images allows styling of those geometries on the fly. <a href="http://polymaps.org/">Polymaps</a>, the only display client I've found so far that can consume vector tiles out-of-the-box, renders these tiles as SVG elements. Because of this, unique styling can be applied via CSS; controlling the color, stroke, fill, etc. of each geometry in response to both attributes associated with the geometry (see image below) or user input... ala the <a href="http://polymaps.org/ex/statehood.html">Polymaps example page</a>.</p>

<p>[caption id="attachment_393" align="alignnone" width="691" caption="USGS real-time gauge stations. Darker dots represent stronger streamflow, lighter dots represent slower flow. You'll have to ignore the fact that I'm symbolizing streamflow without the streams."]<a href="http://www.mkgeomatics.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/usgs.png"><img src="http://www.mkgeomatics.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/usgs.png" alt="" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>The above example converts data from the <a href="http://waterservices.usgs.gov/rest/WOF-IV-Service.html">USGS Instantaneous Values Web Service</a> (part of the <a href="http://waterdata.usgs.gov/nwis/">USGS Water Date for the Nation program</a>) as a JSON response to GeoJSON. These data points are then symbolized dynamically using Polymaps. More on that later.</p>

<p><code>javascript
{
"type": "FeatureCollection",
"features": [{
"geometry": {
"type": "MultiPolygon",
"coordinates": [
[
[
[-122.973093, 47.969842],
[-122.973093, 47.969842]
]
]
]
},
http: //jsbeautifier.org/
"type": "Feature",
"properties": {
"property_s": "USFS",
"juris_name": "Olympic National Forest"
},
"id": 1280
}]
}
</code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TMS: Shaded Relief for OSM Data (An Adventure and A 1/2)]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkgeomatics.github.io/blog/2008/12/19/tms-shaded-relief-for-osm-data-an-adventure-and-a-12/"/>
    <updated>2008-12-19T17:00:15-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkgeomatics.github.io/blog/2008/12/19/tms-shaded-relief-for-osm-data-an-adventure-and-a-12</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After reading <a href="http://stamen.com/">Michal Migurski's</a> excellent post, '<a href="http://mike.teczno.com/notes/hillshading.html">making friends with hillshading</a>' I decided to try my own hand at producing a TMS-compatible hillshade layer for OSM. Motivated by both the high resolution LiDAR data which I happen to have access to, and the lack of access to ArcDesktop during the winter intersession... I set out on the FOSSGIS path. <!-- more --></p>

<p>[caption id="attachment_205" align="alignnone" width="259" caption="The resulting overlay"]<a href="http://www.mkgeomatics.com/apps/openlayers/tiles/ol_working.html"><img src="http://www.mkgeomatics.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2008/12/picture-1-259x300.png" alt="The resulting overlay" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>The final output was created in a primarily two-step process. The hillshade was created using Matt Perry's <a href="http://www.perrygeo.net/wordpress/?p=7">GDAL DEM tools</a>. This command line addition to the GDAL suite of tools negated having to import the DEM into a new GRASS location, and exporting the resulting hillshade back out as another format.</p>

<p>The majority of the work, the tiling that is, was done using <a href="http://www.klokan.cz/projects/gdal2tiles/">GDAL2Tiles</a>. This Google Summer of Code project operates under a command line utility which will take your slick GDAL-compatible raster dataset as input, and export a set of tiles exactly to your specs. What's more is the capability to automatically generate google maps and OpenLayers viewing pages which can be directly uploaded to a webspace.</p>

<p>Finally, applying a slight transparency to the OSM layer allowed for the shaded relief to appear from behind. Quick-and-Dirty, <a href="http://mkgeomatics.com/apps/openlayers/tiles/ol_working.html">but it works</a>!</p>

<p>The pain came when trying to compare the local TMS overlay using OSM vs. Google Maps base data. While using Google Maps street data, we clearly see the LiDAR building footprints align with the vector street centerlines. But switching over to OSM data, we see a drastic skew between the two.</p>

<p>[caption id="attachment_206" align="alignnone" width="300" caption="Google Street Data: Properly Aligned Local TMS"]<a href="http://www.mkgeomatics.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2008/12/picture-21.png"><img src="http://www.mkgeomatics.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2008/12/picture-21-300x209.png" alt="Google Street Data: Properly Aligned Local TMS" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>[caption id="attachment_209" align="alignnone" width="300" caption="OSM Data: Note Hawaii Belt Road's location compared to its LiDAR footprint."]<a href="http://www.mkgeomatics.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2008/12/picture-4.png"><img src="http://www.mkgeomatics.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2008/12/picture-4-300x297.png" alt="OSM Data: Note Hawaii Belt Rd's location compared to its LiDAR footprint." /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>Initially, I assumed that the problem was the result of some projection issues (EPSG: 4326 vs EPSG: 900913), until I realized that all data sets (LiDAR, Google, and OSM) had matching coastlines. Any distortion resulting from the affine transformation between WGS84 and Spherical Mercator would have clearly showed up along the coast as well as the streets.</p>

<p>A quick look at the <a href="http://wiki.openstreetmap.org/wiki/Potlatch">Potlatch</a> editor revealed the inaccuracy of the TIGER line files used in this section of the map:</p>

<p>[caption id="attachment_210" align="alignnone" width="300" caption="Potlatch: TIGER data is a good, but not great."]<a href="http://www.mkgeomatics.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2008/12/potlatch.png"><img src="http://www.mkgeomatics.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2008/12/potlatch-300x273.png" alt="Potlatch: TIGER data is a good, but not great." /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>All-in-all I was extremely impressed with the speed and efficency of using the <a href="http://www.perrygeo.net/wordpress/?p=7">GDAL DEM Tools</a> as well as <a href="http://www.klokan.cz/projects/gdal2tiles/">GDAL2Tiles</a>. Both projects are great representations of what can be done by individuals who choose to build upon existing FOSSGIS projects, and give back to the community.</p>

<p>Additional Note:
A GRASS-based approach to creating a TMS layer is possible, and has been outlined in <a href="sunbird.jrc.it/pvgis/doc/paper/2008_OSGeo5_TiledMapServices.pdf">this paper</a> appearing in the OSGeo Journal.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ScapeToad - Open Source Cartogram Generator]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkgeomatics.github.io/blog/2008/11/23/scapetoad-open-source-cartogram-generator/"/>
    <updated>2008-11-23T05:11:25-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkgeomatics.github.io/blog/2008/11/23/scapetoad-open-source-cartogram-generator</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://chorogram.choros.ch/scapetoad/index.php">ScapeToad</a> provides an amazingly easy to use interface for creating cartograms. Accepting shapefiles directly as input, it has a wide variety of fine-tunable settings in addition to its presets. The ability to utilize multiple layers as weights also seems like a pretty exciting feature. Written entirely in java, it's platform-independent, another plus for mac and / or linux GIS users. <!-- more --></p>

<p>[caption id="attachment_127" align="alignnone" width="300" caption="Above: The counties of Washington State."]<a href="http://www.mkgeomatics.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2008/11/wa.jpeg"><img src="http://www.mkgeomatics.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2008/11/wa-300x202.jpg" alt="WA_Green" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>What is so cool about this program is that not only does it use shapefiles as an input, but it generates shapefiles as output as well. A SizeError attribute is also generated to allow a user to easily control map symbology using GIS software. In addition to this, one can also export as an SVG directly to use in a graphics editor.</p>

<p>The cartogram below was generated using the percentage of a county's total area covered by state routes. The lighter colors indicate a smaller distortion in size while the darker colors indicate a larger distortion in size. Note the I-5 corridor in Western Washington is heavily affected using this criteria.</p>

<p>[caption id="attachment_128" align="alignnone" width="300" caption="Above: The result. "]<a href="http://www.mkgeomatics.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2008/11/cartogram2.jpeg"><img src="http://www.mkgeomatics.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2008/11/cartogram2-300x212.jpg" alt="WA_Cartogram" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>ScapeToad - <a href="http://chorogram.choros.ch/scapetoad/index.php">http://chorogram.choros.ch/scapetoad/index.php</a></p>

<p>Data (WA DOT) - <a href="http://www.wsdot.wa.gov/">http://www.wsdot.wa.gov/</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
