<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Events | mattmakesmaps]]></title>
  <link href="http://mkgeomatics.github.io/blog/categories/events/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mkgeomatics.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-30T23:25:01-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://mkgeomatics.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Matthew Kenny]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[matthewkenny AT gmail DOT com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ESRI UC Student Assistant, Sweet!]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkgeomatics.github.io/blog/2009/04/27/esri-uc-student-assistant-sweet/"/>
    <updated>2009-04-27T03:13:59-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkgeomatics.github.io/blog/2009/04/27/esri-uc-student-assistant-sweet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just found out that I'll be participating in the 2009 ESRI UC as a student assistant. Big thanks go out to <a href="http://geography.asu.edu/balling">Dr. Robert Balling</a> and <a href="http://www.spatiallyadjusted.com/">James Fee</a>, who both wrote letters of recommendation for me.</p>

<p>Now to get back to more pressing matters, like refactoring this giant wad o' javascript. <!-- more --></p>

<p>See you in San Deigo!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OSM 'Minutely' Tile Updates: Thanks CloudMade!]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkgeomatics.github.io/blog/2009/01/24/osm-minutely-tile-updates-thanks-cloudmade/"/>
    <updated>2009-01-24T13:32:07-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkgeomatics.github.io/blog/2009/01/24/osm-minutely-tile-updates-thanks-cloudmade</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Another great OSM Mapping Party is underway in Tempe Arizona. Brandon of <a href="http://www.cloudmade.com/">CloudMade</a> came out to run the show, with local hosting by <a href="http://www.spatiallyadjusted.com/">James Fee</a> of RSP Architects. Coffee, pizza, libations, and Open Source GIS provided a great foundation for lively discussion on the practical and philosophical aspects that OpenStreetMaps provides. <!-- more --></p>

<p>Of particular interest was a question posed by a first time OSM'er, who wondered why we had to wait a week for the tiles to render, just to see the results of some type of experiment that we might be trying out in the digitization and attribution of features in the map. Well, no one could really give him a good answer other then, 'it's just the way it is'.</p>

<p>It appears though, that CloudMade has provided us with an answer just the other day. The <a href="http://matt.sandbox.cloudmade.com/">Minutely Updated Tile Server</a> is updated 'every minute from OpenStreetMap diffs'. The results can be seen below. The first image depicts the standard weekly update view while the bottom image depicts the minutely render. Note the presence of the additional buildings on ASU's Tempe Campus.</p>

<p>[caption id="attachment_241" align="alignnone" width="300" caption="Above: OSM Weekly Update"]<a href="http://www.mkgeomatics.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2009/01/weekly.jpeg"><img src="http://www.mkgeomatics.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2009/01/weekly-300x242.jpg" alt="Above: OSM Weekly Update" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>[caption id="attachment_242" align="alignnone" width="300" caption="Above: CloudMade's Minutely Updated Tile Server for OSM"]<a href="http://www.mkgeomatics.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2009/01/minutely.jpeg"><img src="http://www.mkgeomatics.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2009/01/minutely-300x240.jpg" alt="Above: CloudMade's Minutely Updated Tile Server for OSM" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>Check out the full post from CloudMade's blog here: <a href="http://blog.cloudmade.com/2009/01/23/nearly-live-tiles/">http://blog.cloudmade.com/2009/01/23/nearly-live-tiles/</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OSM Recap]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkgeomatics.github.io/blog/2008/12/08/osm-recap/"/>
    <updated>2008-12-08T02:01:36-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkgeomatics.github.io/blog/2008/12/08/osm-recap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What an awesome weekend. There was a good turnout for the Phoenix OSM mapping party, put on by <a href="http://www.cloudmade.com/">CloudMade</a> and hosted locally by <a href="http://gangplankhq.com/">Gangplank</a>. On both days we saw a mixture of GIS professionals and Open Source users come out to support the project. A new neologism to add to the list also came out of the event, 'crowdsourcing'. <!-- more --> The work of many locals who have an inherent expert knowledge of their surrounding environment replacing the work of what would otherwise be performed by a few skilled professionals.</p>

<p>Here is the result of our work:</p>

<p>[caption id="attachment_199" align="alignnone" width="300" caption="Above: ASU Mapping Party"]<a href="http://www.mkgeomatics.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2008/12/export.png"><img src="http://www.mkgeomatics.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2008/12/export-300x225.png" alt="ASU Mapping Party" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>In any event, we decided to focus our efforts on ASU's campus for the weekend. Before we went out with GPS units, an OSM'er named 'jfuredy' had actually taken a stab at some rooftop digitization of buildings along campus. I've already noticed that there are inherent conflicts that occur by digitizing from rooftops. Tall buildings of course, will appear oblique, with their roofs offset from their actual footprints. This creates scenarios in which buildings (created from oblique angled rooftops) are overlapping walkways.</p>

<p>[caption id="attachment_200" align="alignnone" width="215" caption="Above: Digitization Conflict"]<a href="http://www.mkgeomatics.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2008/12/picture-2.png"><img src="http://www.mkgeomatics.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2008/12/picture-2.png" alt="Above: Digitization Conflict" /></a>[/caption]</p>

<p>I'm excited to continue working on the OSM project, and hope to see more mapping parties in the future. Speaking with <a href="http://cloudmade.com/team/brandon-aguirre">Brandon</a>, our contact at CloudMade, I mentioned that the end of January could be a potential date. This would be the first week of the new semester for MAS-GIS, and hopefully more of the students will come out and support the project!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OpenStreetMap.org Mapping Party This Weekend]]></title>
    <link href="http://mkgeomatics.github.io/blog/2008/12/04/openstreetmaporg-mapping-party-this-weekend/"/>
    <updated>2008-12-04T06:29:01-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://mkgeomatics.github.io/blog/2008/12/04/openstreetmaporg-mapping-party-this-weekend</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.meetup.com/OpenStreetMap-Phoenix/">http://www.meetup.com/OpenStreetMap-Phoenix/</a> It's going to rock. It really is.</p>

<p>Having just heard of OSM a little over a month ago, and using their tiles for about two weeks now... I'm really excited to give back to the OSM community. In a way, it's a chance for those who have never committed code to a FOSS project (like me) to really add some positive input back <!-- more --> into a community that we are a part of, if only in a small way. But hey, if we are all contributing small bits to the project-at-large... it'll add up. A little '<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neogeography">neogeography</a>', anyone?</p>

<p>Additionally, I have put together a small tool to compare the current OSM offerings to that of various commercial mapping vendors (Google, Microsoft VE). Pretty fun exploration of the OpenLayers API!</p>

<p>Check it out here: <a href="http://mkgeomatics.com/apps/openlayers/osm_compare.html">http://mkgeomatics.com/apps/openlayers/osm_compare.html</a></p>

<p>[caption id="attachment_196" align="alignnone" width="300" caption="Above: Quick and Dirty OSM Tool"]<a href="http://www.mkgeomatics.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2008/12/osm_tool.jpeg"><img src="http://www.mkgeomatics.com/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2008/12/osm_tool-300x244.jpg" alt="Above: Quick and Dirty OSM Tool" /></a>[/caption]</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
